Thank you.
© transcript Emily Beynon
All right now, y'all fresh niggas, y'all gonna be in a cutting game.
Very simple.
I want you to take your knife, get in them cane, make it sing.
Take the cane out.
Cut my tops, clean the shucks off.
Throw it on a pile for the planting game.
Nah, them king ain't gonna jump up and bite you.
Don't shy back.
Rush in, boys, rush in.
My lord, sunshine.
My lord, lord, lord.
My pa, be dead.
My lord, sunshine.
My Lord, be right.
His name is Christ.
His heart is good.
My Lord, sunshine.
My Lord, love of God.
My mouth, be there.
My palm, be there.
My Lord, sunshine.
My Lord, be there.
I'm sorry.
¶¶
I love you.
Thank you.
I'm sorry.
.
All right, all right, all right, all right.
All right.
Thank you for the music.
Come on.
Get in there.
Give me a kiss.
I love you, Margaret.
I love you too, my love.
Sleep well.
I'll take this.
I don't want to hear any more noise.
Good night.
Three weeks and two days.
It is the custom.
I wonder what you'll do without me.
I won't stay idle.
Darling, it's good money.
If only I didn't have to share your cooking with other people.
You don't.
Be good for your mother.
Okay, Alonzo?
Can I get a kiss, please?
Thank you. Travel safely.
Stay safe.
Ready?
Get out.
Good day, Mr. Northup.
Devil call his name that he is known. Mr. Northup!
I have two gentlemen whose acquaintance you should make,
Mrs. Brown and Hamilton.
Sir?
Mr. Northup, these two gentlemen
were inquiring about distinguished individuals,
and I was just this very moment saying
Solomon Northup is an expert player on the violin.
He was indeed.
Mr. Moon is being overly gracious.
Well, take it into consideration his graciousness.
Your modesty may we trouble you
for a moment of your time to converse, sir?
Of course.
Good.
A circus?
That is our usual employee, the company currently in the city of Washington.
Suck is too constricting a word to describe the talented and merry band with which we travel.
It is a spectacle unlike most have ever witnessed.
Creatures from the darkest Africa get unseen by civilized men,
acrobats from the Orient who contort themselves in the most confounding manners.
And I myself, in aid of Mr. Brown, an internationally renowned practitioner in the art of prestidigitation.
We are on our way thither to rejoin the company,
having left for a short time to make a small profit from our own exhibition.
The reason for our inquiry with Mr. Moody.
Yes, we had just a devil of a time in procuring music for entertainments.
Men of true talents are seemingly in short supply.
Thank you, sir.
If we could persuade you...
to accompany us as far as Washington.
We could give you $1 for each day's services
and $3 for every night played at our performances.
In addition, we will provide sufficient pay
for your return here to Saratoga two weeks from today.
Welcome to Washington, Solomon.
Today?
I didn't go too much!
Some say not enough.
Solomon, $43 all to you.
That is far more than my wages amounted.
It's been a most profitable week.
Cheers.
Another.
Gentlemen, your generosity is extraordinary.
And your talents are undeniable.
To Solomon.
Cheers.
Oh.
It's all right, Solomon.
There's no shame in it.
No shame at all.
I'm sorry.
Hamilton, we must hurry.
One too many libations?
Halfway there.
I'm so sorry.
Shh, shh, shh.
We won't hear it.
We won't.
Let him sleep, Hamilton.
A good night's rest.
And tomorrow...
Tomorrow you will feel as well and refreshed
as if the Earth were new again.
Hamilton, there's nothing more we can do for him.
Such is the pity.
Well, boy, how you feel now?
My name...
My name is Solomon Northam.
I'm a free man, a resident of Saratoga, New York,
the residence of my wife and children, who are equally free.
And you have no right whatsoever to detain me.
You're not any free man.
And I promise you, I promise you upon my liberation,
I will have satisfaction for this wrong.
Resolve this.
Produce your papers.
You're no free man.
And you ain't from Saratoga.
You're from Georgia.
You ain't a free man
You're nothing but a Georgia runaway
You're just a runaway nigger
From Georgia
Come on.
You stay!
You, Georgia, stay!
Hey! Hey!
Are you a slave?
No.
Fuck!
Help me.
Somebody help me.
Help!
That old thing of yours is just rags and tatters.
You need something proper to wear.
Go on, put it on.
There.
That's fine.
Got no gratitude?
Oh, that's from my wife.
Oh, rags and tatters.
Rags and tatters.
Go on, wash up.
The boy, too.
Get him clean.
Scrub now.
You know my mama will come?
Then hush him up.
Mama.
Quiet.
Hush him up.
Mama.
My mother will come.
I swear she will, but you must be silent.
Be silent.
We need a sympathetic ear, an opportunity
to explain our situation.
Who, in your estimation, is that sympathetic ear?
The two men I journeyed with.
I'm certain they're making inquiries at this very moment.
I'll be just as certain they're counting
the money paid for delivering you to this place.
They were not kidnappers.
They were artists, fellow performers.
You know that?
You know for certain who they were?
The reality to come is us being transported southward.
New Orleans, if I was to venture, after we arrive,
we'll be put to market.
And beyond that, well, I suppose once in a slave state,
there's only one outcome.
I don't say that to give you empty agitation, John.
For y'all, for y'all, there ain't nothing but the help
of John Wilson kidnapped.
John's just being held as dead, that's all.
Master P, it's doesn't John be redeemed.
Boy, our masters will not come for us.
John, John, I'm sorry for your help,
but that's how it be where you're going
when you're going without John.
Mama!
Brian.
Are you all right?
Come on, get up.
I said get up!
No, no, don't.
No, I don't want to hear you talk.
Get in the yard.
Not my children.
Ain't no need for all that.
Just taking a little trip, that's all.
Don't want to frighten the children over a little boat
ride, do you?
That's master's going to pay his debt.
Hurry up. Line up.
This master's going to pay his debt.
What?
Get up.
I don't want to hear a word out of none of you.
Not a one.
I'm sorry.
Let's go.
All right, come on.
Move.
Come on.
Come on, child.
Come on. Follow your mama.
Come on, boy.
Come on. Up these stairs.
Get out of that wagon. Come on.
Come on, move it.
Let's go. Come on. Up the stairs.
Get up.
Come on, let's go.
Let's go.
Get up the gate.
Come on, move it.
All right, come on.
Move it, boy.
Oh, yeah.
Hey, you, go on.
Get up.
Sit down right there.
Whee.
Come on.
Right there, sit down.
I'm sorry.
Cheer, and don't be so cast down.
If you want to survive, do and say as little as possible.
Tell no one who you really are and tell no one you can read and write.
Unless you want to be a dead nigga.
Now keep your mouth shut.
I say we fight.
The crew is fairly small.
We're well planned. I believe they could be strong on.
Three can't go against the whole crew.
The rest of you are niggas.
Born and bred slaves. Niggas ain't got no stomach for a fight.
Not a damn one.
Boss, I know.
We get we were traveling.
We wish we'd die trying.
Survival's not about certain death.
It's about keeping your head down.
Days ago I was with my family.
In my home.
Now you tell me all is lost.
Tell no one who I am. That's the way to survive.
Well, I don't want to survive.
I want to live.
All right.
Come on.
Better off.
Better than us.
you
I don't see him.
Clemens! Clemens Ray!
Clemens!
Who's in charge here?
I'm the captain.
I'm Mr. Jonas Ray.
My solicitor has documentation verifying the Negro known as Clemens Ray is my property.
I know nothing of this arrangement.
You are ordered to return that property immediately or be charged with thievery.
Free him!
Mr. Reza.
All right, that's it.
Clamos! Clamos!
Get him back!
Clamos!
I'm sorry.
There's no dance.
Mr. Parker.
Ah, Mr. Northup.
Mrs. Northup.
Solomon, can I interest you in a new crew bag?
Pure silk by way of the French.
We're in need of a fresh carry-off.
My missus is Travis.
Nothing more.
The year has passed already.
Off to work at Sandy Hill again?
I am.
I have just the thing.
Something to suit your style and yet sturdy enough for the 40-mile round trip.
It's beautiful.
At what price?
We will take it.
Children, come see what your father has just purchased for me.
One moment, sir.
You'll be assisted.
Mr. Parker.
Sir.
If we could discuss the price.
Forgive me, Solomon.
Mrs. Northup, a customer waits.
Welcome, sir.
Shop well, sir, but mind your wallet.
Hey, no attention to this gentleman's nonsense.
Jesper!
My regrets for the intrusion, sir.
No intrusion.
Good day, sir.
Good day.
Jesper.
Very good, very good.
Let's see here. Eliza!
Stand up when you hear your name. Eliza.
Leffy.
John.
Oren.
Platt.
Stand up.
You fit the description given. Why didn't you answer when called?
My name's not Platt. My name...
Your name is Platt.
Captain, get these niggers to my cart.
I believe I have something very much to your liking in the back room.
Follow me, please.
Yes.
Inspect them at your leisure.
But I ask you to pay particular regard to young Ezra here.
Incredibly sound limbs.
I have never seen anything quite like him.
And this marvelous creature, can you believe it?
Hmm?
She'll make a fine lady's maid.
Yes, madam.
So inspect at your leisure.
Take your time, help yourself to refreshments.
Gentlemen, what catches your fancy here?
Hmm? This boy?
Yes, open your mouth.
Open, wider.
Look in there.
Never been sick a day in his life.
And I call particular attention to Martha.
She is an excellent pastry cook.
Ah, Mr. Ford.
Splendid seeing you, sir. What catches your fancy? This lad is very brawny.
How much are the wands, Platt and Eliza?
Ah, yes. A thousand for Platt.
Uh-oh.
This is a nigger of considerable talent, I assure you.
700 for Eliza?
My fairest price?
You will accept a note?
Please, sir.
Of course, from you, Mr. Ford.
Do not divide my family.
Do not take me unless you take my choice.
Eliza, quiet!
You will have the most faithful slave in me,
the most faithful slave that has ever lived.
But I beg that you do not separate us.
Your price for the boy?
Please.
I will give you something to cry about.
Randall, come forward.
Come, come, come, come, come.
Now, you see how fit this boy is?
You know, like ripe fruit.
May I take your stick? A moment?
Observe this, Randall. Jump, jump, jump, run, run.
Very good. Higher.
Do you see this? Very likely, he will grow into a fine beast.
Ah, 600 for the boy.
Fair and final.
Done.
Superb. A moment, please.
Mr. Ford.
Please. Eliza!
How much for the little girl?
You have no use for her. One so young will bring you no profit.
No, no, no, no. I cannot sell the girl.
There's heaps and piles of money to be made from her.
She's a beauty, one of the regular bloods.
No, none of you thick-lipped, bullet-headed, cotton-picking niggers here.
Child, man.
For God's sake, you're not sentimental at least.
My sentimentality extends the length of a coin.
Now do you take this lot? Mr. Fordow, do you pass on them all?
Please, please, please.
I will take the wands, plait and the lice.
It's all the lice and the plaits, Gwendolyn.
You will not take them from me!
Get around her!
Please, please, no!
No, please!
No!
That's not me!
I will keep reserving the cry about your goddamn wands!
Get out of here, kid! Out, now! Now!
Mr. Ford.
Pleasure.
Did you bring all those niggers?
Two of them.
You got two.
Mr. Chapin.
This one's crying.
Why is this one crying?
Separated from her children.
Oh, dear.
Couldn't be helped.
Poor poor woman.
Mr. Chapin.
Yes, sir.
Tomorrow you can take these two up to the mill,
start them working.
For now, make the matter quick.
Fix him a meal and have him rest himself.
Yes, sir.
Come on now.
Come on.
Don't dawdle.
Something to eat and some rest.
Your children will soon be forgotten.
Now, for all of you raw niggers that don't know,
my name is John Tibby,
William Ford's chief carpenter.
You will refer to me as Master.
Now, Mr. Chapin,
is the overseer on this plantation.
You two will refer to him as master.
So clap your hands.
Like this.
Come on.
Come on, now. Clap your hands.
Nigger run, nigger flew,
nigger tore his shirt in two.
Run, run, the paddy roller'll get you
Run, nigga, run, well, you better get away
That's right, like you mean it
Nigga run, run so fast
Stove his head in a hornet's nest
Run, run, the paddy roller'll get you
Run, nigga, run, well, you better get away
Run, nigga, run, the paddy roller'll get you
Some folks say a nigger don't steal
I caught three in my cornfield
One has a butcher and one has a pack
One has a rope, it was hung around his neck
Run, nigger, run, the patty roller
Catch you, run, nigger, run, well, you better get away
Hey, Mr. Patty Roller, don't catch me
Catch that nigger behind that tree
Run, nigger, run, the patty roller
Run, nigger, run, well, you better get away.
Run, nigger, run, the patty roller'll catch you.
I am the God of Abraham, the God of Isaac,
and the God of Jacob.
Run, nigger, run, the patty roller'll catch you.
And when the multitude heard this,
they were astonished at his doctrine.
Run, nigger, run, well, you better get away.
And then one of them, which was a lawyer,
asked him a question, tempting him.
Run, nigger, run, the patty roller'll catch you.
Run, nigga, run away from me, baby.
The creek is plenty deep enough to sail,
even with a boat full of load.
The distance from the work area to the point on the latter bayou
is several miles by water fewer than land.
It occurs to me that the expense of transportation
would be materially diminished.
Materially diminished?
If we use the waterway.
Are you an engineer or a nigger?
Let the man say his piece.
It's a scheme.
Plenty of engineers have schemed similarly.
The passes are too tight.
I reckon them are more than 12 feet at their most narrow.
Wide enough for a tub to traverse if a team of niggers cleared it out.
And you know what of transporting terraformin'?
I labored repairing the Champlain Canal on the section over which William Van Nortwyk was superintendent.
With my earnings, I hired several efficient hands to assist me,
and ended into contracts for the transportation of large rafts of timber from Lake Champlain to Troy.
Well, I'll admit to being impressed even if you won't.
Well, collect the team and see what good you can do.
When I saw you, I saw you.
All right, keep it up.
Two, three, four.
For me, too late.
For me, I'd live or die.
Lay down and cry.
Hey, boy, I'm proud, my lord, so proud.
I'm strong, yes, sir.
I'm tall, yes, sir.
My lord, my lord, my lord.
But you are a marvel.
We're high, too high.
What took you so long?
Thank you, Master Voight.
Oh, thank you.
Yeah.
Yes, sir.
I'll be happy.
Come on.
Oh, that's a wonderful thing to do.
It's flat.
My great thanks, Master Ford.
My thanks to you.
It is the least of it.
I hope it brings us both much joy over the years.
Yeah.
Thank you, Matthew.
Oh, God.
Wait.
Eliza.
Stop!
You let yourself be overcome by sorrow, you will drown in it.
Have you stopped crying for your children?
You make no sounds, but will you ever let them go in your heart?
They are as my flesh.
Then who is distressed?
Do I upset the master and the mistress?
You care less about my loss than their well-being?
Master Ford is a decent man.
He is a slaver!
Under the circumstances.
Under the circumstances, he's a slaver.
But you truckle at his boot.
No.
You luxuriate in his favor.
I survive!
I will not fall into despair.
I will offer up my talents to Master Ford.
I will keep myself hearty till freedom is opportune.
Oh, Ford is your opportunity?
You think he does not know that you are more than you suggest?
But he does nothing for you.
Nothing.
You are no better than prized livestock.
Call for him.
Call.
Tell him of your previous circumstances
and see what it earns you, Solomon.
So you settle into your role as Platt then?
My back is thick with scars for protesting my freedom.
Do not accuse me.
I accuse you of nothing I cannot accuse.
I have done dishonorable things to survive,
and for all of them I have ended up here.
No better than if I had stood up for myself.
God forgive me.
Solomon, let me weep for my children.
I can't help that kind of depression about.
But whoso shall offend one of these little ones,
it were better for him that a millstone were hanged
about his neck and he were drowned
in the depth of the sea.
Amen.
Make them boards flush.
They are, sir.
Now, they is no such thing.
They're as smooth to the touch as a yearling's coat.
Why are you calling me a liar, boy?
That's all a matter of perspective, sir.
From where you stand, you may see differently,
but the hands are not mistaken.
I simply ask that you use all your senses
before rendering judgment.
Oh, my, you are a brute.
You are a dog.
And no better for following instruction!
I'll do as ordered.
Well, then you'll be up at daybreak.
You'll procure a keg of nails from Chapin
and commence to putting on clabberts.
Yes, sir.
Make them boards flush.
Please, please, please say, where am I going?
Where am I going?
Say, Solomon!
Solomon!
When I say I had my master's favor, you understand.
And for nine years, he blessed me with every comfort
and luxury in life, silks and jewels
and even servants to wait upon us.
Such was our life.
And the life of this beautiful girl I bore for him.
My master Barry's daughter.
She always looked at me with an unkind nature.
And she hated Emily,
no matter she and Emily were flesh or flesh.
As Master Barry's health failed, she gained power in the household,
and eventually I was brought to the city
under the false pretense of our free papers being executed.
My poor children.
I love you.
I thought I told you to commence the putting on clappers.
Yes, master, I'm about it.
These have all been replaced.
Well, didn't I tell you to get a keg of nails?
And so I did.
So you did.
God damn you.
I thought you knowed something.
I did as instructed.
If there's something wrong, it's wrong with the instruction.
You black bastard.
You goddamn black bastard.
Strip your clothes.
Strip.
I will not.
You will not live to see me.
I'll see you another day, nigga!
Oh, God, help!
Oh, shit!
Help!
Murder!
Oh, shit!
Oh, God!
What does it matter?
Master Tibbies wants to whoop me
for using the nails you gave me.
They say, don't buy half.
I will have flesh.
And I will have all of it.
Do not stir.
Do not leave the plantation, for if you run, I cannot protect you.
Stay here.
I love you.
Gentlemen, whoever moves that nigger's a dead man.
I am the overseer on this plantation.
William Ford holds the mortgage on Platt.
If you hang him, he will lose his debt.
You have no claim to his life.
As for you two, if you have any regard for your own safety,
I say be gone!
You got no cause!
The plot is mine, and mine to do with as I please!
You touch.
Sam!
Master Mew, get Master Ford!
Thank you.
All right.
I'm sorry.
Get down.
I believe Tilly's just skulking about the premises somewhere.
He wants you dead, and he will have it so.
It's no longer safe for you here.
I don't believe you will remain passive if Tibby's attacked.
I have transferred my debt to Edwin Epps.
He will take charge.
Master Ford.
You must know that I'm not a slave.
I cannot hear that.
Before I came to you, I was a free man.
Trying to save your life.
And I have a debt to be mindful of.
And that is to Edwin Epps now.
He's a hard man, prides himself on being a nigger breaker,
but truthfully, I could find no others who would take him.
You made a reputation of yourself.
Whatever the circumstances, you are an exceptional nigger, Platt.
But I fear no good will come of it.
And that servant which knew his Lord's will,
which knew his Lord's will,
and prepared not himself
prepared not himself
neither did according to his will,
shall be beaten with many stripes.
Did you hear that?
Stripes.
That nigger that don't obey his lord,
that's his master, do you see?
That there nigger shall be beaten with many stripes.
Now many signifies a great many.
40, 100, 150 lashes.
That's scripture.
Oh, my God.
Pick that gun.
Move along now.
Come on, Redwood.
Drive them.
Pick that gun.
Move along now.
What are you doing, boy? Come on!
240 for Bob.
What you got for James?
295 pounds.
That's real good, boy. That's real good.
182 for Platt.
How much can even an average nigga pick a day?
200 pounds.
This nigga ain't even average.
512 pounds for Patsy.
512!
Your menfolk got no shame letting Patsy out pick you.
They ain't yet come, she swung lower than 500 pounds.
Queen of the field she is.
138 pounds.
I ain't done, Treech.
Ain't I owed a minute to luxury aid on the work Patsy done?
Yes, sir.
Damn queen.
Born and bred to the field.
Nigger among niggers.
And God gave her to me.
Lesson in the rewards of righteous living.
All be observant to that.
All.
Now, Treech, now speak.
138 pounds for Phoebe.
Hit 145 yesterday. Pull her out.
206 pounds for George.
How much you pick yesterday?
Six pounds for George.
2.29.
Get him out.
Come on, get.
Come on.
Come on, boy, move.
No!
Mm-hmm.
Get up!
We danced tonight!
Get your fiddle pack!
Get up!
Come on!
Come on, Vlad, come on!
Come on, where's your merriment? Move your feet!
Sell her.
What's all this?
You will sell the niggers.
Sell little Pats?
She picked with more vigor than any other nigger.
Choose another to go.
No other.
Sell her.
I will not.
You will remove that black bitch from this property,
or I'll take myself back to Cheneyville.
Back to that hog's trough where I found you.
Do not set yourself up against Patsy, my dear.
Because I will rid myself of you well before I do away with her.
What you looking at?
Damn woman.
I won't have my moon spoiled.
I will not.
Dance.
Dance, I said.
Come on.
Pick it up, Quack.
Play that little boy.
Whoo!
Platt.
Yes, Mistress?
Can you find your way to Bartholomew's?
I can, ma'am.
This is a list of goods and sundries.
You will take it to be filled and return immediately.
Take your tag.
Tell Bartholomew to add it to our debt.
Yes, Mistress.
Where you from, Platt?
I told you.
Tell me again.
Washington.
Who were you master?
Master Namor Freeman.
Was he a learned man?
I suppose so.
He learn you to read?
A word, here or there.
But I've no understanding of the written text.
Don't trouble yourself with it.
Same as the rest. Master brought you here to work, that's all.
Any more, I'll earn you a hundred lashes.
Thank you.
Come here, boy.
Come on.
Where you going, boy?
On my way to Betholomus.
Sent by me, Mrs. Epps.
You best get there, then.
Get that queen.
All right, black red and silver, yeah.
And tobacco, two ounces.
Fool's cap paper.
Any trouble?
No, ma'am. No trouble.
I love you.
I'm sorry.
Flat Epps. Good Sunday morning.
Master Shaw. Master sent me to retrieve Patsy.
May I approach?
You may.
Excuse me, Mistress Shaw.
Nigga Platt?
Patsy, Master wishes you to return.
This Sabbath day, I was free to roam.
Master sent me running to fetch you.
Said no time should be wasted.
Drank your tea?
Thank you, Mistress, but I don't dare.
Would you know Master Epps' consternation to be any lessen with your time to return?
Anger's his constant condition.
Sit.
Sit and drink the tea that I offered.
Wouldn't be Epps' concern.
I'd rather not say.
Little gossip on the Sabbath be fine.
All things in moderation.
As you are aware, Master Epps is a man of hard countenance.
You know he has ill feeling towards your husband?
He do.
Master Epps has somehow come to believe that Master Shaw is something of a Lothario.
A misguided belief, no doubt.
No doubt.
If not born out of truth, it's there.
I meant no disrespect.
He ain't heard you.
Oh, I meant no disrespect to you, mistress.
Got no cause to worry for my sensibilities.
I ain't felt the end of a lash in more years than I can recall.
I ain't worked the field neither.
Well, once I served, now I have others serving me.
The cost to my current existence be Master Shaw broadcasting his affections
and me enjoying the pantomime of his fidelity.
If that would keep me from cotton picking niggas, that would it be.
Small at reasonable price be paid for Shaw.
I know what it like to be the object of Master's predilections and peculiarities.
peculiarities, a lusty visit in the night,
a visitation with the whip.
Take comfort passing, good Lord will manage apps.
In his own time, good Lord will manage them all.
The curse of the Pharaohs, but a poor example
of what wait for the plantation class.
This is nice.
That's it.
Don't look in his direction.
Continue on.
That's it.
Found him, master.
Brought her back just as instructed.
What'd you just now tell her?
What'd you say to Pats?
No words were spoken, none of consequence.
You're a liar.
You're a damn liar.
I saw you talking with her.
I'm not talking to you.
I'm talking to you.
Tell me.
Can I speak of what did not occur?
I'll cut your black throat!
Master!
You come here.
Master, I thought... I said come here!
I brought her back, just like you...
Come here!
Come on, let's go!
Master!
I got her, just as instructed.
Stay away from Pat's boy!
Stay away from pets, boy.
Put Matthew out.
It's the Lord's day.
I ain't nothing Christian in us carrying on like this.
I could see to you.
In the name of Allah,
I'll be master to his feet.
I'm gonna kill you!
What? What's the fuss?
Master Epps believed Patsy and me to be in conversation when we were not.
I tried to explain, but it's led to all this.
What is it? You can't remain the Sabbath without her under your eye?
Hold it.
You are a no-account bastard.
A filthy, godless heathen. My bed is too holy for you to share.
What's he been telling you?
Of your misbegotten ways.
And he would know what of anything?
I ain't even spoken with him today.
You lying nigga, Platt.
Have I?
There. There's all the truth he got.
Dead nigga.
Thank you.
I'm sorry.
That's it.
I can't do it.
I love you.
I'm sorry.
Thank you.
A moment from the dancing.
Come sample what I baked for y'all.
Thank you, mistress. Thank you, mistress.
Thank you, mistress. There'll be none for you, Patsy.
You see that?
You see that look of insolence she give me?
Say nothing but return away.
Are you blind or ignorant?
It was hot, hateful scorn.
It filled that black face.
You tell me you didn't see it, it's because you choose not to look.
Or are you saying I lie?
Whatever it was, it passed.
Is that how you are with the niggers?
Letting every ill thought fester inside them?
Look at them.
They foul with it.
They foul with their hate.
You let it be, it's going to come back to us in the dark of night.
You want that?
You want them black animals to leave us gut-like pigs in our own sleep?
Oh, you are manless.
A damned eunuch, if there ever was.
If you won't stand for me, I pray you'd at least be a credit to your own kind
and beat every foul thought from them.
Beat it from him!
Eat.
Fill yourselves.
And then we dance.
I said eat.
Platt.
Platt, you awake?
I have a request.
The act of kindness...
I secret it from the mistress.
Return it?
It's yours, Blatt.
For what cause?
Oh, I ask.
End my life?
Take my body to the margin of the swamp?
Take me by the throat?
Hold me low in the water until I'm still and without life?
Bury me in a lonely place of doubt.
I will do no such thing.
The gory detail with which you speak.
I'll hold on it long and hard.
It is melancholia.
Nothing more.
How can you fall into such despair?
How can you not know?
I ain't got no comfort in this life.
Thank you.
If I keep by mercy from you, I'll beg it.
There are others.
Beg them.
I'm begging you.
Why?
Why would you consign me to damnation with such an ungodly request?
There is God here.
God is merciful.
And he will give merciful acts.
Won't be no hell for you.
Do it.
Do what I ain't got the strength to do myself.
It's a plague.
It's a cotton worm.
It's damn biblical.
Two seasons God done sent a plague to smite me.
What I done that God hates me so?
It's that godless lot.
They brought this on me.
I brought them God's word, and even as they are, they brought me God's score.
Damn you! Damn you! Damn all y'all!
Judge.
Mr. Epps.
I am deeply saddened to hear about your misfortune.
The price don't reflect your concern.
Listen up.
You're Judge Turner's for the season.
More if need be till my crops return.
Y'all bring no disrespect to me.
Y'all bring no biblical plagues to him, you hear?
I'll take it out of your skin.
Get out.
I'm sorry.
I'll get you a new boot.
Cloud, is he?
Yes, sir.
You cultivate cane previously?
No, sir, I've not.
That comes to you quite naturally.
You educated?
No, sir, niggas are hired to work, and I read or write.
You play the fiddle.
Yes, sir. Yes, I do.
Willie Johnny, the plant up the bayou,
celebrates his anniversary in a three weeks time.
I'll hold out your name to him.
What you earn is yours to keep.
Yes, sir.
Mind yourself, Platt.
I'm going to go ahead and do that.
Thank you.
I'm going to go get some water.
Joyous day.
Dark times is behind us.
Clean living and prayer done lifted the plague.
As thick and white as New England snow.
Now my niggas has returned to me.
I heard Judge Turner gave you favor.
Jubigali and Blant, with your slick nigger ways.
Well, you won't stand idle, boy. Not on my land.
Much work to do.
Days of old long since, huh?
Joyce, Joyce, indeed!
Whoo!
Let's go find something sweet for you.
Mm-hmm.
Candy.
Candy?
Oh, pick this cotton.
Pick this cotton.
Man ain't mean, boys.
Man ain't mean.
Oh, man ain't mean, boys.
Oh, work this cotton.
Work this cotton.
Oh, work ain't hard, boys.
Work ain't hard.
180 pounds.
Patsy.
520 pounds for Patsy.
That's my girl.
Don't ever let me down.
Platt?
160 pounds.
Ormsby.
64 pounds.
A midday's labor would average 200 pounds.
Yes, sir.
I'm sure in time he'll develop as a picker,
but it takes effort, boy.
Put some damn effort into it.
Yes, sir.
Take him out. Get to whooping.
It's a tragedy.
How does such come to pass?
Working the field and picking cotton like a lowly hand?
I am of a damn sight better station.
I've worked as an overseer, you know.
I did not know, sir.
Not, sir.
Just arms fee.
Not owed more than any other.
in the field.
How did you arrive at such a place, if I may ask?
Ask?
It's just a conversation.
I became a little too dependent on the whiskey,
a little too undependable on the job.
Now, before you say I'm just a sorry drunkard,
let me state my case.
As what liable employment is overseeing is,
it is no easy chore on the spirit.
I say no man of conscience can take the last
to another human day in, day out
without shredding at his own self.
Takes him to a place where he either makes excuses
within his mind to be unaffected
or he finds some way to trample his guilty sensations.
I trampled with frequency.
I gave in to tales of wealth and prosperity,
But such profitable outcomes are reserved for plantation masters.
It's the lot of the rest of us to serve.
Now all I want is to earn a decent wage and get myself home.
The proceeds of my fiddling performances.
Just a few picayunes.
But all I have in the world,
I promise them to you if you will do me the favor I require,
but I beg you not to expose me if you cannot grant the request.
What is it you ask?
First, your words, sir.
On my honor.
It's a simple enough request.
I only ask that you deposit a letter at the post office of Marksville
and that you keep the action an inviolable secret forever.
A patron is what I require, sir.
I'll do it.
And I'll accept whatever payment's offered.
To assist you, I put my own self at risk.
I will do so.
But fair compensation is all I ask.
I'll be back in a minute.
Draw up your letter.
We'll meet again in two days.
In two days.
Thank you.
¶¶
I love you.
Well, boy.
I understand I gotta learn a nigger that writes letters,
tries to get white fellas to mail them.
Well, Ormsby told me today the devil was among my niggers.
But I had one that needed watching while he was running away.
When I asked him why, he said,
you come over to him, wake him up in the middle of the night,
and want him to carry a letter to Martville.
What you got to say to that?
There's no truth to it.
You say
How could I write a letter without ink a paper
Who am I gonna write to I got no friends living as I know
That arms bees on the line drunk
He wants you to hire him as an overseer
You know, when I said he wants to make you believe we're all going to run away so you'll hire him as an overseer,
he believes you're a soft soap, and he's given to such talk.
Made this story out of whole cloth because he wants the situation.
It's all a lie, Master.
It's all a lie.
I won't be damned.
Were he not free in the white plant...
were he not free and white.
© transcript Emily Beynon
I'm going to sit here.
Sun down the mountain.
Sun gonna set here.
Teach me, Lord.
Get him water.
I just work here.
Get up.
Teach me, Lord.
I'll be back here.
Nigga, get up!
What you looking at, boy?
I'll be back here.
He picking, boy.
I just want to say something about Uncle Avery.
He was a good man.
And he always looked out for us ever since we were little.
God love him.
God bless him. God keep him.
Amen.
Went down to the river Jordan
Where John baptized three
where I walked the dirt
says John he baptized me.
I say roll Jordan roll.
Roll Jordan roll.
My soul will rise in heaven Lord for the year.
Jordan roll.
Well some say John was a Baptist.
Some say John was a Jew.
But I say John was a preacher cause my Bible says so too.
I say roll, Jordan, roll, roll, Jordan, roll.
My soul will rise in heaven, Lord, for the year when Jordan rolls.
Hallelujah.
Roll, Jordan, roll, roll, Jordan, roll.
My soul will rise in heaven, Lord, for the year when Jordan rolls.
Hallelujah.
Roll, Jordan, roll.
Roll Jordan roll, my soul will rise in heaven Lord for the year when Jordan rolls.
Everybody say roll Jordan roll, roll Jordan roll, my soul will rise in heaven Lord for the year when Jordan rolls.
Roll Jordan roll
My soul will rise in heaven Lord
For the year when Jordan rolls
Roll Jordan roll
My soul will rise in heaven Lord
For the year when Jordan rolls
Right to the end.
Oh, yeah.
Hey, Bass.
Oh, no, no, no.
No shame in taking respite from the heat.
Drink, shave.
It's ungodly for travelers, party or otherwise.
And what's funny?
Epps, I merely mean to finish the work at hand,
as requested and as paid for.
If something rubs you wrongly,
I offer you the opportunity to speak on it.
Well, you asked plainly, so I will tell you plainly.
What amused me just then was your concern for my well-being in this heat,
when, quite frankly, the condition of your laborers...
The condition of my laborers?
It is horrid.
The hell?
It's all wrong. All wrong, Mr. Epps.
They ain't hired help.
They're my property.
You say that with pride.
I say it as fact.
If this conversation concerns what is factual and what is not,
then it must be said that there is no justice, no righteousness in this slavery.
But you do open up an interesting question.
What right have you to your niggers when you come down to the point?
What right?
I bought them. I paid for them.
Of course you did, and the law says you have the right to hold a nigger.
But begging the law's pardon, it lies.
Suppose they pass a law, taking away your liberty,
making you a slave.
Suppose.
That ain't a supposable case.
Laws change, Epps.
Universal truths are constant.
It is a fact, a plain and simple fact,
that what is true and right is true and right for all.
White and black alike.
You compare me to a nigger, Bass?
I'm only asking in the eyes of God, what is the difference?
Might as well ask what the difference is between a white man and a baboon.
I seen one of them critters in Orleans know just as much as any nigger I got.
Listen, Epps, these niggers are human beings.
If they are allowed to climb no higher than brood animals,
you and men like you will have to answer for it.
There is an ill, Mr. Epps, a fearful ill resting upon this nation,
And there will be a day of reckoning yet.
You like to hear yourself talk, Bass.
Better than any man I know of.
You'd argue that black was white or white black.
If anybody would contradict you.
I found supposition if you lived among Yankees in New England.
But you don't.
most
I surely do not.
Where is she?
Where is Pat?
Where is she, Kevin?
Where is she?
Pete, Pete, where is she?
Where is Pat?
What are you standing there for?
We know nothing of her, Master.
Know nothing of what?
We know nothing of her.
Of what?
Where is she going?
I don't know.
She ran off, ain't she?
She ran off.
Where is she?
I don't know, Master.
Do you know anything of her?
You know, you know, you know, you know, you know!
No, I don't!
You miserable black dogs.
Stand like the deep and dumb.
Speak!
She gone.
My Paz is gone.
Run off. Run off, did you?
Mr. Epps.
You miserable wench. Where you been?
I've been nowhere.
Nowhere!
Last year, Miss Deeds.
The Sabbath day, Master.
I took me a walk to commune with the Lord.
Bring the Lord into you, Deceptians.
You're coming from Shaw's plantation.
No!
Now you speak!
Now you want to add to her lies, you find your tongue.
I went to Master Shaw's plantation.
You admit it.
Yes.
Freely.
And you know why.
I got this from Mistress Shaw.
Mistress Sepp won't even grant me no soap to clean with.
I stink so much I make myself gag.
Five hundred pounds of cotton, day in, day out.
More than any man here.
And for that I will be clean.
That's all I ask.
This here, what I went to Charles for.
Liar.
The Lord knows that's all.
You're a liar.
And you, blind with your own covetousness.
I don't lie, Messer.
If you kill me, I'll stick to that.
Well, I'll fetch you down.
I don't need you to go to Shaw's.
Treach!
Run, fetch some wine.
Edward!
Strip her, strike her bare, and lash her to the post.
Oh
You don't miss yourself
Do it.
Strike the life from her.
Bader.
Give her the whip, give it all to her.
Platt, you come here and you beat her now.
Platt!
Come here!
I'd rather hit you, Platt.
You strike her.
Strike her.
He pantomimes.
There's barely a welt on them.
That's what your nigger's making you.
Fool for the taking.
Striker, Black, striker!
He will strike her.
He will strike her until her flesh is rent
and meat and blood flow equal,
and I will kill every nigger in my sight.
You understand me?
Strike her! Strike her!
Tell us I know more.
I ain't said nothing.
Give me that weapon.
Give me.
Get up.
Get me the weapon.
Ow!
Ah!
Hey! Hey! Hey!
Hey! Hey!
Thou devil!
Sooner or later,
someone in the course of eternal justice
thou shalt answer for this sin.
Hey!
Sin? There is no sin.
Man does how he pleases with his property.
The moment, Platt.
I'm of great pleasure.
You be goddamn careful.
I don't want to come a lot in my mood no further.
I'm sorry.
Ah!
Ah.
I'm sorry.
That's the best.
I want to ask you what part of the country you come from.
No part of this land.
I originate from Canada.
Now guess where that is.
Oh, I know where Canada is.
I've been there myself.
Montreal and Kingston and Queenston and a great many places.
Well, travel for a slave.
Slave, how came you here?
Master Bass.
If justice had been done, I never would have been here.
How's this?
Tell me all.
I'm afraid to tell you.
Every word you speak is a profound secret.
Your story, it...
It is amazing, and in no good way.
Do you believe, sir, in justice, as you've said?
I do.
Slavery is an evil that should befall none.
I believe so.
You truly do.
Then I ask, I beg...
that you write my friends in the North,
acquainting them of my situation...
and beseeching them to forward free papers.
It would be an unspeakable happiness to see my wife and my family again.
I traveled this country for the best part of 20 years.
My freedom is everything.
The fact that I can walk out of here tomorrow
brings me great pleasure.
Life doesn't mean much to anyone.
It seems yours might mean a lot to a whole lot of people.
But what you're asking me, sir, scares me.
And I must say, I am afraid.
Not just for you, but for me.
I will write your letter, sir.
And if it brings you your freedom, it will be more than a pleasure.
It will have been my duty.
Now, would you kindly hand me those shingles?
All right.
Thank you.
Shhh...
Come on.
Platt!
Where's the boy called Platt?
Come here, boy.
Your name is Platt, is it?
Yes, sir.
You know that man?
Mr. Barclay.
See you again, sir.
Again?
Mr. Parker.
That man received a letter compiling many accusations.
You look me in the eye.
And on your life, you answer me truthfully.
Have you any other name than Platt?
Solomon Northup is my name.
Sheriff, what's all this?
It's official business.
My nigga, my business.
Your business waits.
Tell me of your family.
Platt, I have a wife, two children.
What the hell?
What are your children's names?
Margaret and Alonzo.
What was your wife's name before her marriage?
I am who I say.
Where you going, Platt?
Go authorize you to interfere with my property.
My authority.
Platt, you come back here.
Platt, you come back here, boy.
You will unhand him.
Platt is my nigger.
He is Mr. Solomon Northam.
You say you come here unfamiliar to me and make claims.
Not no doubt.
It's the man is Solomon Northam.
The hell he is.
He's my nigger, and I'll fight you for it.
As is your right.
as it will be my pleasure to bankrupt you in the courts.
Your decision.
Unhand him.
I know you had some hand in this, Blatt.
I'm gonna get to the bottom of it.
Pay him no mind.
I paid good money for this nigger.
Courthouse got papers to prove it.
And we got papers proving he's free.
I own you. You belong to me.
You hear me, Blatt?
Unhand him.
I'll have 200 shots across your back by sundown.
Blatt!
Get my horse, Treach.
Oh.
Get away from him, Pats.
I'll be seeing you real soon.
Solomon, we need to make haste.
No.
Solomon.
Thank you.
I love you.
All right.
I apologize for my appearance, but I have had a difficult time these past several years.
Margaret.
Alonzo.
Who's this?
He's my husband.
Husband.
It is very good to meet you, sir.
We have much acquainted to do.
Yes, sir.
And this is your grandson, Solomon Northupston.
Solomon.
Forgive me.
There's nothing to forgive.
¶¶
© transcript Emily Beynon
Thank you.
I went down to the river Jordan where John baptized three.
When I walked the devil in hell, said, Johnny, baptize me.
I said, row, Jordan, row.
Row, Jordan, row.
My soul will rise in heaven, Lord, for the year when Jordan rose.
Well, some say John was a Baptist.
Some say John was a Jew.
But I say John was a preacher.
My Bible says so, too.
I say, roll, Jordan, roll.
Roll, Jordan, roll.
My soul will rise in heaven, Lord, for the year when Jordan rolled.
Hallelujah.
Roll, Jordan, roll.
My soul will rise in heaven, Lord, for the year when Jordan rolled.
My soul will rise in heaven, Lord, for the year when Jordan rose.
Hallelujah.
Roll, Jordan, roll.
My soul will rise in heaven, Lord, for the year when Jordan rose.
Everybody say roll, Jordan, roll.
Roll, Jordan, roll.
My soul will rise in heaven, Lord, for the year when Jordan rose.
Hallelujah.
Roll, Jordan, roll.
My soul will rise in heaven, Lord, for the year when Jordan rose.
Thank you.